<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe treatise against the priesthood and sacrifice of the Church of Rome vvherein the simple may perceiue thir intollerable impietie, usurping that office and action, which ever appertaine to Christ only, by G.G.</title>
            <author>Gifford, George, d. 1620.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01374</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11495</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120395</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855594</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855594</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21094</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01374)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21094)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1486:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe treatise against the priesthood and sacrifice of the Church of Rome vvherein the simple may perceiue thir intollerable impietie, usurping that office and action, which ever appertaine to Christ only, by G.G.</title>
                  <author>Gifford, George, d. 1620.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>Newly reprinted.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[2], 39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. I[ones] for Andrevv Kembe dwelling by the Sessions House in Long South-Warke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1635.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>G.G. = George Gifford. Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Another issue, with cancel title page of the edition of 1634 (STC 11494).</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A treatise against the Romish priesthood and sacrifice.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; trimmed at top affecting running title and pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21094:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21094:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE TREATISE AGAINST THE Prieſthood and Sacrifice of the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> VVherein the ſimple may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thir intollerable impietie, uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that office and action, which ever appertaine to Chriſt only, By <hi>G. G.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Newly reprinted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. I.</hi> for ANDREVV KEMBE dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Seſſions Houſe in Long <hi>South-Warke.</hi> 1635.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:21094:2"/>
            <head>A BREEFE TREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TISE AGAINST THE Prieſt-hood and Sacrifice of the Church of Rome.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Pope and his clergie doe ſtiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirme and goe about to maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that they bee Prieſts, and that it is an holy Prieſthood which they have: even the Prieſthood of the <hi>New Testamnet</hi> Further alſo they boaſt, that the ſacrifice which they offer, is the ſonne of God himſelfe, even Chriſt Ieſus, God and man, fleſh, bloud, and bone, as he was borne of the bleſſed Virgin. We on the contrary affirme that they be very <hi>Baalamites,</hi> and not Prieſts of the New Teſtament: and that their ſacrifice is not the ſonne of God, but the ſtinking and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous ſacrifice of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> Who ſhall be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? we or they? Let neither of both for our ſelves have any credit at all. For what is man, that he ſhould have any credit? Let neither of us be our owne Iudge, for then there would be partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: But let God onely ſtrike the ſtroke, let him alone pronounce the ſentence, let that part be cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited which hath his witneſſe and teſtimony. When he ſpeaketh, let man keepe ſilence: When he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth ſentence, let the mouth of all fleſh be ſhut
<pb facs="tcp:21094:3"/>
up: For who ſhall reply againſt the words of his mouth, which are in perfect trueth and wiſedome? His teſtimony hath he expreſſely ſet downe in the ſacred Scriptures, his voyce hath he there uttered, to declare his perfect minde and will: Let them be brought forth, and heard, ſearch them, for ſo are ye willed. Crave the true underſtanding at his hands, who is the onely teacher. If by them it be manifeſtly proved unto you, that the popiſh Prieſts be not the Prieſts of the New Teſtament, nor their ſacrifice the ſonne of God, then let men no longer doubt, but that all their whole worſhip is idolatrous and Antichriſtian. For if their prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and ſacrifice, which are the two principall things be awry, what can be good in them? Let us come to the triall of the matter. And firſt in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall (which they deny not) the word doth teach, that the dignity, privilege, and office of the holy Prieſt, is to approch into the preſence of God, to offer giftes, and ſacrifice, and to make requeſt and ſupplication for the people. The neceſſity of this office doth come from the profaneſſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity of men. All men are uncleane ſinners, God is moſt pure and holy, and doth perfectly hate ſinne: And for the ſame cauſe he doth curſe and reject all thoſe which are polluted therewith. They can not approch, nor indure his preſence, before whom no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing uncleane can ſtand. The prayers which come from them cannot be heard, being the prayers of ſinners, and therefore not cleane. No gift can be accepted at their hands, to make any reconcilement or to get any favour, they and all theirs are ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected,
<pb facs="tcp:21094:3"/>
they muſt either have ſome other to do it for them, or elſe for ever remaine ſtill out of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and be utterly caſt away in eternall perdition. He that ſhall do it, muſt be without ſpot or ſinne, and therefore among all the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> is found worthy and able to execute this office. For if we reſpect this great worke of reconciliation betweene God and men, we ſhall finde that alone he hath wrought it, and therefore is the onely Prieſt of God. None other can in ſuch conſideration be called Prieſts. It is true in deede that <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſonnes were conſecrated and made Prieſts, and did execute the Miniſtery of the Prieſthood in the Temple: But yet as their ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices did not, nor could not take away ſinne, being but ſhadowes and the reſemblance of the ſacrifice of Ch<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſt, ſo alſo they were not ſacrifices in deede, but ſo called, for that they were the patterne of that which is the true ſacrifice. The ſame is to be ſaid of the Prieſts, that they were no o her Prieſts, but in figure, becauſe they did reſemble Chriſt, who alone is a Prieſt in truth. Thoſe o her Prieſts were ſeparated from the people, and conſecrated to the ſervice of the Temple. The cheife of them might enter into the moſt holy place, and come before the <hi>Arcke</hi> of the covenant and the mercy ſeate, and there offer with bloud to make reco<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ciliation. They bare the names of the tribes of Iſrael, and ſo preſented them before the Lord. But yet all was but a ſhadow, to direct the eyes of their faith unto Chriſt: for theſe Prieſts could not waſh away ſinne, they could not bring men into heaven, and
<pb facs="tcp:21094:4"/>
therefore when he came, which is the Prieſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, and which doth accompliſh that which was by them but reſembled: then all thoſe ſhadowes did ceaſe and give place. He continueth a Prieſt for ever. He hath perfectly wrought the worke of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, and brought men into favour with God. For with the ſacrifice of his body he hath ranſomed them, and with his bloud he hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged away their ſinnes with full ſatisfaction, and his prayers have beene accepted: He hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved honour and power to ſave for ever all thoſe whom he doth ſanctifie. Now the queſtion is, whether any can be joyned with him in this office, and be partakers with him in this high dignity, as to offer up to God the ſame ſacrifice which he offered. For this is without all controverſie, that ſuch as do challenge a copartnerſhip with him in offring the ſacrifice, and gift which he did offer, do alſo challenge a fellowſhip with him in the dignity and glory of the Prieſthood by which he did offer <note place="margin">Heb. 9. 1 4.</note>it. For was not the great glory of his Prieſthood in this, that he offred himſelfe in ſacrifice unto his father? ſhall not thoſe then which do the ſame thing receive the ſame honour and glory therfore? Thus we ſee that when as none could be found <hi>worthy in heaven and earth, but onely the Lambe,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">v. 6. 7.</note>
               <hi>Revelat.</hi> 5. yet every greaſie ſhaveling will have fellowſhip and glory with him, even in the higheſt part of his office. Lord how long wilt thou ſpare? looke downe and viſite the blaſphemy of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Beast,</hi> upon him, and upon the heard and route of his horned ſhavelings. They ſay they be Prieſts,
<pb facs="tcp:21094:4"/>
doubtleſſe then are they mediators of the New Teſtament<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For the Teſtament and the Prieſt are <note place="margin">Chriſt onely the Prieſt of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</note>joyned together, the Prieſt of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment is the mediatour of the New Teſtament. For Chriſt is compared with <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſonnes, to have obtained a miniſtery ſo much more excellent, <hi>as he is the Mediatour of a better Teſtament, Hebr.</hi> 8. 6. The excellency of the miniſtery of <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſonnes, was according to the worthineſſe of the Teſtament, whereof they were the Mediators. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, they could not have that honour to be Prieſts, or mediators of that Teſtament, wherein there was but <hi>the ſhadow of good things to come, Heb.</hi> 10. 1. unleſſe it had beene given them of God: as it is expreſſed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. where he ſpeaketh of that Prieſthood of the lawe, which hath now ceaſed. Seeing none could have this honour to be a Prieſt of the old Teſtament, but ſuch as were called of God as was <hi>Aaron:</hi> then how much leſſe ſhall any be partakers of this dignity with the ſonne of God to be the Prieſts &amp; mediators of the new covenant, but ſuch as can ſhew that God hath given them this honour? <hi>Chriſt did not take this honour to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, Hebr.</hi> 5. <hi>but he that ſaid, Thou art my ſonne, this day have I begotten thee, gave it him.</hi> The Lord ſware that he ſhould be a prieſt. Let the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts ſhew any calling which they have of God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this glory of the Priſthood: Let them ſhew any <note place="margin">Chriſt ordaine<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no Prieſt in th<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>one place out of the new Teſtament, where Chriſt did ordeine Prieſts: Finally, let them ſhew where ever <hi>Peter</hi> or <hi>Paul,</hi> or any Apoſtle or miniſter of the Goſpel, have called themſelves prieſts, or have
<pb facs="tcp:21094:5"/>
been ſo called by others, otherwiſe than that which they give unto all the faithfull, that being waſhed and ſanctified in the bloud of Chriſt, they be made Kings and Prieſts unto God. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>Revel.</hi> 1. &amp; 5. which is in another ſence than this which they challenge. No, the word of the Lord is directly againſt you, ye prieſts of <hi>Baal.</hi> For it ſpeaketh of one Prieſt which ſhould ariſe after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> and not of prieſts. It ſaith, there is <hi>one Mediator betweene God and man,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. And therefore alſo it followeth, that there is but one <hi>Prieſt.</hi> Becauſe the Prieſt of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the mediator of the ſame, is there any man ſo mad as to aſcribe this glory to the Pope and his prieſts, as to ſay they be mediators of the new Teſtament? If not, then are they no prieſts. Now, although this is ſufficient to proove their prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood to be counterfait, that they can ſhew no cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the word, nor no mention that any one of the Apoſtles was a prieſt, or that any man ſhould have ſuch honour: yet to make the matter more evident, I will ſhew by further reaſons, that their prieſthood is ſuch, that it cannot ſtand with the prieſthood of Chriſt. We all know, that the Lord ſwore that his ſonne ſhould ariſe up a <hi>Prieſt for ever after the order of Melchiſedech, Pſal.</hi> 110. Then if it fall out, as it ſhalbe manifeſtly ſhewed, that the Prieſthood of the Papacy is directly contrary unto that order of <hi>Melchiſedech:</hi> It muſt needs alſo fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that the ſame is not of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The order of the prieſthood of <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> is gathered out of that which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith of him, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 14. the words
<pb facs="tcp:21094:5"/>
are theſe: and <hi>Melchiſedech King</hi> of <hi>Salem</hi> brought foorth bread and wine, which was alſo a prieſt of the moſt high God. And he bleſſed him, ſaying, Bleſſed be <hi>Abram</hi> of the moſt high God, poſſeſſor of heaven and earth, and bleſſed be the moſt high God, which hath delivered thine adverſaries into thine hand, and he gave him tythe of all. This man was greater than the Patriarch <hi>Abraham,</hi> as it is proved by two reaſons, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7. the one that <hi>Abraham</hi> paid him tithes: The other, that he bleſſed <hi>Abraham.</hi> Then <hi>Moſes</hi> writing of ſo great a man not mentioning father nor mother, nor kindred, beginning, nor end of his life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> although he had a father and a mother, and kinred, and had both a beginning and an end: yet becauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneth not any of theſe, it is ſaid, that he was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out father, without beginning of dayes, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end of life, as though he were one that had ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly come downe from heaven. When it is ſaid, that he was a <hi>Prieſt</hi> of the moſt high <hi>God,</hi> no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made of any annoynting, of any miniſtring garments, of any temple, altar, or ſacrifice, not yet of any that did ſucceed him, it is gathered that he doth continue a prieſt for ever. And moreover, that in his Prieſthood all things are ſpirituall and full of endles power. By this argument, the holy Ghoſt proveth <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. <hi>ver.</hi> 16. 17. 18. that the prieſthood of the Levites was abrogate, and could not ſtand with the Prieſthood of Chriſt, ſeeing it could give no ſtrength nor furtherance thereto: for the one being ſpirituall, and according to the power of the life that is not diſſolved, the other, as
<pb facs="tcp:21094:6"/>
he ſpeaketh being after the law of the carnall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, they could not be joyned ſo together as that the one might be a ſupply unto the defect of the other. For although the law of the carnall commandement, which is ſo called, not in reſpect of the founder thereof, which was God, but for that the ſubſtance of the things were bodily and carnall) did profit and benefit men thus farre, that by outward carnal things, they had the reſemblance of things ſpirituall to ſtrengthen their faith. Yet when he was come, in whom was all the ſpirituall and heavenly power of the Prieſthood, thoſe car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and earthly things were to ceaſe. As for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: <hi>Aaron</hi> was annointed with materiall oyle, he was clothed with the miniſtring garments, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into a tabernacle upon earth which was built with hands, he had the bloud of calves and goates, &amp; ſlaine beaſts for ſacrifice, he preſented the names of the tribes before the mercy ſeat. All theſe and ſuch like are the carnall commandement, theſe did not take away ſinne, nor reſtore into favour with God: But Chriſt alone is the prieſt that wrought that. His annoynting was not with oyle, but with the holy Ghoſt: He needeth no holy garments, for there was no ſpot of uncleanneſſe in him to be covered. He came not with the bloud of ſlaine beaſtes, but with his owne bloud. He entred not into the Tabernacle made with hands, to appeare for us, and to preſent us before the Arke: but he is entred into the very heavens, even unto the throne of God, to preſent us there. Thus then it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that the Prieſthood of <hi>Aaron,</hi> being after the
<pb facs="tcp:21094:6"/>
law of the <hi>carnall commandement,</hi> that is to ſay, the conſecration was with things that were earthly and of a bodily ſubſtance, the ſacrifices alſo of the ſame ſort, it could do nothing. But the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of Chriſt, wherein all things are heavenly and ſpirituall, and full of <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e power, hath ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and perfectly accompliſhed the worke of recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation. If this order then of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there is nothing carnall, did aboliſh the order of the Prieſthood of <hi>Aaron,</hi> wherein all things were carnall, becauſe the carnall things cannot helpe at all to bring men to heaven, and becauſe the order of the one Prieſthood did ſo differ from the other, as being of a quite contrary nature: It muſt needs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that the Prieſthood of the Papacy cannot ſtand with the Prieſthood o<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Chriſt,</hi> becauſe it is alſo carnall. For was the oyle upon <hi>Aaron</hi> carnall, and is not their annointing and ſh<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ving carnall? Were all the miniſtring garments of <hi>Aaron</hi> carnall, and are not their veſtments, as the <hi>Cope,</hi> the <hi>Surpleſſe,</hi> the <note place="margin">Note this.</note>
               <hi>Amiſſe,</hi> and other ſuch holy and prieſtly robes car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall? Was the Altar in the Temple carnall, and all the miniſtring veſſells that did belong thereto, and are not the Altars of theſe carnall? Were <hi>Aarons</hi> incenſe and oblations carnall: and are not the obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of theſe, and all their incenſe, and other things carnall. Thoſe former could not ſtand with the Prieſthood of the new Teſtament, becauſe they were in ſubſtance carnall: how then ſhall theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which are as carnall as they? Tell us O ye <hi>Baalamites</hi> of the Romiſh order, wherefore your or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhould in any reſpect be called the order of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21094:7"/>
               <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> ſeeing it is as contrary unto it as was that of <hi>Aaron?</hi> The order of <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> is gathered out of the deſcription of <hi>Moſes</hi> to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any annoynting with oyle, without garments for the miniſtration, without Tabernacle, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Altar, without ſacrifice, without any earthly thing, And why? becauſe his order is ſpirituall, and therefore all things thereto belonging muſt be ſpirituall. it is eternall and full of endles power, and therefore nothing which appertaineth to the execution thereof muſt be tranſitory and weake. For ſhall an earthly Temple, an Altar of ſtone, gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſilke, or of any corruptible thing be fit to be joyned with that priſthood which is everlaſting? There is no doubt, but that every thing for the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the office, muſt be agreable unto the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Prieſthood it ſelfe: and therefore as there is nothing mentioned in <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> that is carnall, ſo alſo we ſee that our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, a Prieſt after that order hath executed that function without any ſuch things conſecrated therunto. How ſhall the Papiſts then which have their prieſthood executed altogether in ſuch things as be tranſitory, challenge to be of that order with our Saviour, wherein as the Prieſthood is heavenly and eternall, ſo are all things thereto belonging.</p>
            <p>But peradventure ye will ſay: <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> was a Prieſt, &amp; he offred ſacrifice to God as other prieſts at that time. Wherfore ſhould it then be gathered that there was no carnal thing in ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce belonging to the execution of his function? He had an Altar, he had beaſts to offer, and no doubt did offer.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21094:7"/>
I Anſwere that albeit <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> did execute the prieſts office, after the manner of other prieſts, yet that is nothing to the purpoſe. For the order of his prieſthood is gathered out of that deſcription of <hi>Moſes</hi> in which there is no mention of ſuch things. We are not to doubt but that he had father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he was borne as an other man, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo had an end of his dayes: Neverthel ſſe, becauſe thoſe things are left out, he is brought in as one which never had beginning, and that never had end, but continueth a prieſt for ever. In like ſort, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever at any time he executed the office of a prieſt, as others did: yet becauſe there is no ſuch thing expreſſed, and that which is expreſſed, is that wherein he is likened unto the Sonne of God, it is ſaid, that he was a prieſt after another order, and that there was nothing carnall in his p ieſthood. Therefore we are to conclude, that the prieſthood of the new teſtament having nothing in it that is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, the prieſthood of the papacy being and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting altogether of things carnall, and ſuch as were alſo the inventions of men, it muſt needes follow, that they are not prieſts of any teſtament of God, but he prieſts of Antichriſt. Further, let it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that a prieſt muſt ariſe after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> that ſhall ſo continue for ever: For the eternall Sonne of God was reſembled by <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech</hi> in that he is brought in without any beginning: The continuance alſo of his office for ever, in that there is nothing ſaid of his death nor of any that did ſucceede him. This then being manifeſt, what impudent wretches are thoſe which being mortall
<pb facs="tcp:21094:8"/>
men, that have an end, dare ſo blaſphemouſly boaſt, that they be Prieſts after the order of <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech?</hi> how ſhall they ever be able to anſwere unto this? The Prieſt of the new Teſtament is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the order of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> that is to ſay, a Prieſt for ever, without beginning, without end, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any to ſucceede him: Their prieſthood hath a beginning, it hath an end, they have thoſe that do ſucceed one after another. If this be a materiall poynt in that order of prieſthood which Chriſt ſhould be after, as none unleſſe his forehead be of braſſe dare deny, that it ſhould be for ever: What a childiſhnes were it for any man to thinke that the prieſthood of the papacy is the ſame when it doth faile in that which is eſſentiall? For they dye and come to an ende. Are not theſe contrary the one to the other, to continue a prieſt for ever as <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech</hi> in figure, and Chriſt indeed, and to be prieſts for certaine yeares, and then to ceaſe by reaſon of death? Are not then the prieſts made at <hi>Rome</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this order, yea, as contrary as light is unto darkeneſſe, or as heaven is unto hell? And muſt it not ſtill follow, that ſeeing they be no prieſts of the old Teſtament, nor can not be prieſts of the New, unto the which their order is contrary, that their prieſthood may be as good as the prieſthood of <hi>Baal,</hi> and better it cannot be? For if it be not of God, is it not then of the Divell? Let all true Chriſtians therefore behold with deteſtation this helliſh ſacriledge of the Romiſh biſhop, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a prieſt after the divells order, yet ſaieth, he is after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech.</hi> Moreover it is to be
<pb facs="tcp:21094:8"/>
noted, which the holy Ghoſt ſayeth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. ver. 26. that ſuch an high prieſt it became us to have, as was holy, harmeleſſe, unſpotted, ſeparate from ſinnes, and made higher than the heavens. This ſetteth foorth the purity, and alſo the high dignity which of neceſſity are required in that prieſt, that ſhall deale in our cauſe to bring us to God. For if he were a ſinner himſelfe, how ſhould he come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God? If he were ſpotted with any uncleannes, how ſhould he purchaſe favour for others? ſeeing he ſhould himſelfe be out of favour. If he were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy, how ſhould he ſanctify and make holy thoſe whom he doth preſent unto God? In like ſort it is to be weighed, how great that man muſt be of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, that is to enter ever unto the thron<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of glory and there abide, as one able to ſave all that come unto God by him. For thus he muſt be made higher than the heavens, and aboue all creatures in the heavens. For albeit the holy and bleſſed angels be ſeparate from ſinners, and be alſo about the throne of God, yet none of them hath this glory to be made higher than the heavens, none of them then can have the honour of the prieſthood, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine pardon of ſinnes for the Church, that glory and power being reſerved onely to the Sonne who is farre aboue principallities and powers. Such a prieſt as this muſt bring vs that are baſe and ſinfull wretches unto God, in him we muſt be ſanctified; in him we muſt obtaine favour, in him we muſt be heard, that is ſo high in favour, that no requeſt can be denied him. In him we muſt be ſaved who hath received all power and authority both in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb facs="tcp:21094:9"/>
&amp; earth, and liveth for ever. What fouler beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe then can there be than this, that ſinfull, unho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and baſe wormes of the earth, ſhould challenge unto themſelues to be <hi>Prieſtes</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament?</hi> yea, that ſuch filly <hi>Aſſes,</hi> as are ſcarce fit to keepe ſwine, will yet have that office, that the <hi>glorie, honor,</hi> and <hi>power of,</hi> is aboue the <hi>Angels,</hi> let all men judge now of this concluſion. The <hi>Prieſts</hi> of the <hi>New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament,</hi> is <hi>pure and holy, ſeparated from ſinners, made higher than the heavens.</hi> The POPE and all his broode are ſinfull whoremongers, theeues and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, baſe and vile wretches of the earth, farre off from being higher then the heavens. Therefore their prieſthood is not the prieſthood of the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> There is alſo another notable difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the old prieſthood and the newe: that thoſe former did miniſter in earth, in a <hi>Tabernacle</hi> made wi h hands, which had no enduring ſubſtance: This latter is entred into the <hi>Sanctuarie</hi> of <hi>Heaven,</hi> and there doth execute the <hi>Prieſts</hi> office, he doth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing in an earthly ſanctuarie. For why? His <hi>Prieſthood</hi> is heavenly and eternall; his Tabernacle muſt be agreeable unto the ſame. And it is ſaid <hi>that if he were one eareh, he could not be a Priest, wh<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le thoſe Priestes did stand which were after the Law, Heb.</hi> 8. 4. For although our Lord were a <hi>Priest indeed</hi> when he was vpon earth, and did offer the ſacrifice of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, yet ye ſee there was no outward thing that the <hi>Prieſts</hi> vpon earth doe. His body was ſlaine upon earth, but was it caried into the <hi>Temple,</hi> and ſlaine at the <hi>Altar?</hi> Was the blood ſprinkled before the <hi>Arke</hi> of the covenant? No, all things were heavenly and
<pb facs="tcp:21094:9"/>
ſpirituall in this ſacrifice. If we regard the ſubſtance of his body, it was the ſame that ours is. But yet all the vertue and efficacy of the ſame, when it was a ſlaine ſacrifice, was from aboue. And ſo though he were in earth, yet the whole fruite of his worke was in heaven. For he being both <hi>God</hi> and <hi>man,</hi> was a <hi>Prieſt</hi> even then in heaven, when he was ſlaine upon earth. The vertue and power of the ſacrifice to purge away ſinne, was not of the manhood from it ſelfe: but the manhood had it from the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, in that the manhood was ſo united unto the godhead, that they made <hi>one perſon.</hi> In this ſenſe he ſaith, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6. <hi>ver.</hi> 63. <hi>It is the ſpirit that qu cke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, the fleſh profiteth nothing.</hi> Howſoever the fleſh of <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath power in it to give life, as in deede it is the bread of life, and whoſoever doeth eate of it ſhall live for ever: yet it hath not this life of it ſelfe, but from the Godhead. Likewiſe the bloud is able to purge away ſinne, becauſe it is the bloud of a man which is alſo God. It is alſo ſaid, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>The firſt man was of the earth earthly. The ſecond m<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n was the Lord from heaven heavenly.</hi> Wherefore is he called a man from heaven heavenly? was it becauſe his fleſh was from heaven? curſed be he which ſo holdeth. No, it was becauſe all the vertue and efficacy which was in his manhood to redeeme the world, was from heaven. We ſee then that he being ſacrificed in earth, the efficacy of his Prieſthood was in heaven. There is nothing in his Prieſthood, nor in the execution thereof which is earthly. But theſe prieſts are altogether earth, and what can they doe without earth? A
<pb facs="tcp:21094:10"/>
               <hi>Temple</hi> they muſt have on earth, an <hi>Altar</hi> of earth, many other things of earth, which proove that all their miniſtery and function is earthy. Then to <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>riſts Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>od is heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>conclude, the Mediator of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> is not a <hi>Prieſt</hi> upon earth, nor executeth not the <hi>Prieſts</hi> office but in the heavenly <hi>Tabernacle.</hi> The <hi>Romanes</hi> are Prieſts upon earth, they miniſter with earthly things, in earthly <hi>Tabernacles,</hi> and upon <hi>Altars</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to that purpoſe. Who doth not ſee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that they have no affinity at all with <hi>Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, if it may be demaunded, is <hi>ſir Iohn</hi> a King? Surely then have there beene many louſie Kings. Every one which is a Prieſt after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> is a King, for thoſe two are joyned together in his order, the kingdome, and the prieſt hood. Is there any man ſo fooliſh as to take theſe to be kings? They may be taken for prieſts, but not after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> ſo long as they have but ſhaven crownes, and not crownes of gold nor after the order of <hi>Aaron</hi> which is ceaſed: but after the order of the prieſts of <hi>Baal.</hi> If they object that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath both ſwords, the ſpirituall, and the civill, and therefore he is a King and a Prieſt, I anſwere, that therein he is more unlike Chriſt, <hi>whoſe kingdome is not of this world.</hi> The kingdome of Chriſt is ſpirituall, he medled not with the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill ſword, but lef<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it to the Magiſtrate: The <hi>Pope</hi> chalenging it, is not of that order which Chriſt is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <note place="margin">One Prieſt of <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>Seing then, as we have prooved, none can be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers with Chriſt in the moſt high digniry and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Prieſthood, ſeing every Prieſt is a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour of a Teſtament, and of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21094:10"/>
there is but one, ſeeing none can have that honour to be Prieſt, but they which are called of God, and the Papiſtes can ſhew no calling, nor conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crating of Prieſtes in the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi> Seeing in the order of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> all things are ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and full of endleſſe power, in the order of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery all things carnall, <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> continueth for ever, theſe die: Seeing alſo the Prieſt of the New Teſtament muſt be perfectly holy and pure, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot of ſinne, and higher than the heavens, the <note place="margin">Popiſh prieſ<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> are not of G<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>Popiſh Prieſts are abominable ſinners: Chriſt is a Prieſt in heaven, they upon earth: He is both a King and a Prieſt, <hi>ſir Iohn</hi> is not a king: It doth follow, that their order of Prieſthood is not of God: but they be the idolatrous prieſtes of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt. They cannot by their miniſtry and Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood bring men unto God, but contrariwiſe they carry headlong unto the divell. Such therefore as will ſave their ſoules muſt not be blind and wilfull, but open their eyes and behold the claere and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt truth of God, which he hath taught in his word.</p>
            <p>As we have proved this one part, ſo let us now come to the other, that is, to ſhew that the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice which they offer, is not the ſonne of God, but <note place="margin">The popiſh ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice is abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to God.</note>a wicked abbomination, no more pleaſing unto God, than if men ſhould offer a <hi>dogge</hi> in ſacrifice unto him. It might ſuffice to ſatisfie a modeſt minde, that all which they doe is naught, becauſe they doe make themſelves Prieſts after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech:</hi> and ſo do challenge to themſelves greater honour than any <hi>Angell</hi> hath, even the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb facs="tcp:21094:11"/>
that is due alone unto the onely begotten Son of God. And yet where the ſcripture ſheweth that this honour was given unto <hi>Chriſt</hi> with an <hi>oath,</hi> they will have part with him, being not able to bring one ſentence of the word to prove that there ſhould be any Prieſt beſides <hi>Chriſt.</hi> He never or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained any Prieſt, no one of his Apoſtles was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Prieſt, and in every point their order is ſo contrary unto the order of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> this I ſay might ſatisfie: but yet to lay open their trechery further, we will prove that they have abuſed the world, and made them worſhip that for God which was but a cake of flower. I will not goe farre for proofe hereof: for it is manifeſtly and fully to be prooved by that which the holy Ghoſt hath ſet downe as concerning the ſacrifice of the <hi>New Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes.</hi> Thoſe reaſons which are there brought to prove that the ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the law could doe nothing, and therefore were to be aboliſhed, will alſo ſerve to throw downe the abominable idol of the Papiſts. For if the weaknes of thoſe former ſacrifices were gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by their nature and order which was uſed in them, then ſhall the ſacrifice of the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> if it bee found to differ as farre and further from that of <hi>Chriſtes,</hi> than thoſe, be found not to be the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the <hi>New Testament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes, Chap.</hi> 9. <hi>ver.</hi> 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is ſaid, that the former <hi>covenant had alſo ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of religion, and a worldly ſanctuary,</hi> and there he doth repeate particularly ſundry things, as the <hi>Candleſticke,</hi> the <hi>Table,</hi> the <hi>ſhew bread,</hi> the <hi>Golden
<pb facs="tcp:21094:11"/>
cenſure,</hi> the <hi>Arke of the Teſtament,</hi> the <hi>Golden pot with Manna, Aarons Rod</hi> that had budded, <hi>and the Tables of the Teſtament.</hi> In this worldly Sanctuary, with theſe foreſaid ordinances of the ſame nature, did the prieſts of the law exerciſe their office: and this is one argument to prove that their prieſthood was weake and could not bring men unto God. For the habitation of God is in the heavens, there is his throne of glory, and moſt high majeſty thither muſt thoſe be brought which ſhall come unto him, whereupon it followeth, that the Prieſt that ſhall bring men unto God, muſt be a miniſter of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of Heaven. For the entring into the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly place made with hands, and the miniſtring in the ſame with ordinances of the like nature, that is to ſay, earthly and tranſitory, can by no meanes bring men eternally unto God: For how ſhall earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things compaſſe heavenly, or things which va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and decay, bring that to paſſe which ſhall laſt for ever? Thoſe Prieſts therefore, whoſe prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood was tranſitory, for their prieſthood muſt needs be of the ſame nature and condition that their temple and ordinances were, and can ſtand no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than they, were for to ceaſe, when the time was come unto which they were prefixed. Vnto theſe is Chriſt oppoſed in the ſame <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9. <hi>ver.</hi> 24. where he ſaith <hi>that Chriſt is not entred into the holy pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces made with hands, which are ſimilitudes of the true ſanctuary, but is entred into heaven it ſelfe to appeare in the ſight of God for us.</hi> For as the ſacrifice which he offred was heavenly and of eternall power, ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is his Tabernacle, and likewiſe his Prieſthood.
<pb facs="tcp:21094:12"/>
For thoſe three muſt ever be joyned together. Then if the Prieſthood of <hi>Aaron,</hi> and his ſacrifices could doe nothing, but were to ceaſe becauſe their Tabernacle and ordinances were worldly: how much leſſe ſhall the greaſie popiſh prieſtes be able to offer any ſacrifice to appeaſe Gods wrath, ſeeing the ſacrifice which muſt do that, is heavenly and ſpirituall, and cannot be offred in a worldly ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, nor with ſuch ordinances as be of earthie nature? For it is moſt manifeſt that all the trinkets <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>l the Popiſh <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nkets are <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rthly.</note>and traſh of Popiſh Maſſe mongers, wherewithall they do juggle and play with their Mammets are earthly and tranſitory: ſo is alſo their Temple and Altars, and conſequently their Prieſthood. And further alſo it is certaine that the Prieſthood of <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>on</hi> was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d of God.</note>might rather be called heavenly than theirs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was the paterne of the heavenly, and he was called unto that honour of God, but they can ſhew no calling thereto at all. Who then is ſo blinde but may ſee, that ſeeing the ſacrifice propitiatory <note place="margin">The Prieſts <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hite cake o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>er his head is <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> dead idol.</note>cannot be offred by an earthly Prieſt, nor with earthly ordinances, that the white cake which the uncleane ſhaveling the <hi>Baalamite</hi> doth hold up over his head, is not the Sonne of God, but a dead Idol.</p>
            <p>If the blinde idolatous Papiſts will object, that the efficacy of their ſacrifice and prieſthood is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly, although it be executed on earth, they are to be anſwered, that if the efficacy of their prieſt hood be heavenly, then is it eternall, but they are mortall and doe not remaine Prieſts world without ende.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21094:12"/>
Againe, the power of the ſacrifice dependeth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the power of the prieſt, and ſo their ſacrifice is not eternall. This thing ſhall be yet more mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt by a further compariſon which is made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the ſacrifice of Chriſt, and thoſe of the law in the ſame <hi>Chapter. verſe.</hi> 13. and 14. where <note place="margin">Heb. 9. 13. <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>it is ſhewed, <hi>that if the bloud of calues and of goates, and the aſhes of a red Heffer ſprinkling thoſe that were defiled did ſanctifie as touching the carnall purging: then how much more ſhall the bloud of Chriſt, which by his eternall ſpirit, offred himſelfe to God without ſpot, purge your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience from dead workes to ſerve the living God?</hi> This compariſon is brought in to prove that Chriſt by entring once into the holy places, by his owne bloud, hath found eternall redemption: for that being the ſumme of the two verſes going next be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, is proved by this. It was graunted without controverſie, that by reaſon of gods ordinances, the bloud of thoſe poore beaſts, and the water made with the aſhes of the Heffer, being but a dead thing had power in ſome manner to purge, as namely that which he calleth the carnall purging. For if a man were polluted with any outward pollutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and there fore might not come unto thoſe holy things which were the carnall commandements, being but ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes and ceremonies, yet if he were ſprinkled with thoſe, although he were not purged within from ſinne, he was counted cleane: then how much more ſhall the bloud of the ſonne of God, which hath the power of life in it, becauſe it is the bloud <note place="margin">Note this</note>of him that was not only a man ſo holy that he was without ſpot, but alſo God? For herein lyeth the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21094:13"/>
ſtrength of the argument which the holy ghoſt u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to prove that Chriſt at once by his bloud hath purged the conſcience from ſinne for ever, that this ſacrifice was offered by his eternall ſpirit, which is his godhead. For the godhead having eternall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of life, the fleſh and bloud of the manhood joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſo with the godhead that they made one perſon, had alſo the ſame power, ſo that although the bloud of Chriſt of it ſelfe had not power at once to purge eternally, yet becauſe it was the bloud of God, it had that force. Hereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it followeth that the power of that purging by his bloud being eternall, and that one purgation being perfect, the redemption which he hath found is eternal. Hereupon we may ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude againſt the Papiſts, and that with a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble concluſion: Firſt, that ſeeing no ſacrifice hath the vertue to purge away ſinne, but becauſe it is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered by the eternall ſpirit, And ſecondly, that his purging once made, being that which is made by the eternall Godhead, is perfect for ever: By the firſt it is manifeſt that they are not able to offer a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice propitiatory, becauſe they are mortall men, by the ſecond, that there is no place for them, the worke of purging ſinne being already accompliſhed for ever.</p>
            <p>If there be a new redemption to be wrought, then let them be the prieſtes: in the meane time they are foule idolaters, and ſacrilegious wretches, deſtroying the power of Chriſts death, when they will take upon them to do that which he hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy perfectly finiſhed. Come forth ye blinde Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and prove that ye are more than men, ſhew
<pb facs="tcp:21094:13"/>
alſo that the ſacrifice of Chriſt once offered, hath not an eternall and perfect power to purge away ſinne, or elſe confeſſe that yours is Antichriſtian. We may joyne hereu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to that which is uſed to prove that the ſacrifices of the <hi>Leviticall</hi> prieſtes did not purge ſinne: namely, that they were ſo often offered. For thereby the holy Ghoſt doth teach that they were not able to ſanctifie the commers therto, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 1. For then, as he ſayeth, they ſhould haue ceaſed, becauſe there ſhould have beene no more conſcience of ſinne in the worſhippers, being once purged. The reaſon is manifeſt, drawen from the effect of the medicine: for if it have taken away the diſeaſe, and perfected the cure, then is it vaine to adde it any more. If it be ſtill continually, and from time to time applyed to the ſore as ſtill remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, then it may be ſaid truely, that the ſame me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine doth not heale, Wherefore he addeth this proofe, that notwithſtanding the ſacrifices were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred, yet there remained the mention of ſinnes yere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when they kept that ſolemne day of expiation. This diſeaſe of ſinne ſtill remaining as the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all mention and remembrance thereof doeth ſhew: it followeth, that thoſe ſacrifices did nor could not purge it away. Vnto theſe is oppoſed the ſacrifice of Chriſt, which becauſe it hath perfectly purged ſinne for ever, ſo that there remaineth no more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience thereof in thoſe that are ſanctified: it is done but once, and never to be repeated or don againe. The other which were Prieſts in the law ſtood dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miniſtring, and often offring the ſame ſacrifices, which could never take away ſinne. But this man
<pb facs="tcp:21094:14"/>
having offered one ſacrifice for ſinne, ſitteth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver at the right hand of God, from henceforth wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting untill his enemies be made his footſtoole, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 11. 12. The former did ſtand daily mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring as thoſe which had not, nor could not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh the worke of reconciliation, although they offred never ſo often: But he having once of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, ceaſeth from offring, and is ſet downe in the higheſt throne of majeſty and glory, becauſe as it is there ſaid, <hi>he hath with one oblation made perfect for ever thoſe which are ſanctified.</hi> If his ſacrifice did aboliſh ſinne but for a time, as for a yeere, or certaine yeres, then ſhould he either bring nothing to paſſe, or elſe returne often and ſundry times from his glory to offer againe. This is alſo confirmed in the ſame <hi>Chapter. ver.</hi> 18. by a concluſion which is drawen out of the forme of words which the Lord uſeth in the promiſe which he maketh of the New Teſtament: as namely, <hi>that he will remember their ſinnes and their iniquities no more.</hi> He reaſoneth in this manner, where God remembreth not ſinne, there he hath given pardon and remiſſion, for that he collecteth, and where there is pardon, there is no more ſacrifice for ſinne. Now therefore, when we ſee this to be moſt manifeſt by the plaine do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Gods word, let us conſider the abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wickedneſſe of the Papiſts which by their ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice overturne all this. For whereas there is remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes already purchaſed, what place can there be for their ſacrifice propitiatory? whereas that ſacrifice is unperfect, and cannot take away ſinne which is often offred, how is theirs the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21094:14"/>
ſacrifice of Chriſts body, which is continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done againe and againe? What doe they leſſe therefore when they teach, that in the Maſſe they offer Chriſt to his father, to be a ſacrifice to take away ſinne: than affirme that the promiſe of the <note place="margin">Papiſts deny the promiſe<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</note>New Teſtament hath failed, and that ſinne is yet remembred, no remiſſion as yet obtained? And further, when they will needes have him offred ſo often, is it not as much as to deny the effect and power of the bloud of Chriſt? Is it not quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this, that with one oblation he hath made perfect for ever thoſe that are ſanctified? But here they take exception and ſay that they do not offer any new ſacrifice but the ſame. And moreover that their oblation is but an application of the fruit of that which Chriſt offered, and that becauſe we ſee and feele in our ſelues that we are ſtill guilty: all which is but a blinde cavill. For what though they ſay they offer the ſame, did not the Prieſts the Sonnes of <hi>Aaron</hi> yeerely offer ſtill the ſame? doth not the power of the reaſon ſtand in this, to prove that they were not available, becauſe then they ſhould have ceaſed? Can they deny but that they offer often? Further, he doeth not place the perfect worke in the ſacrifice of Chriſt, becauſe it was but one, but becauſe it was but once offred: for he ſaith not with one ſacrifice, <hi>but with one offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Note this</note>
               <hi>hath he made perfect for ever thoſe which are ſanctified.</hi> This doth cut the throte of their often offring, when his one offring had made perfect for ever: for it leaveth nothing behinde for ſuch cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives as they be. And further where they pretend
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21094:15"/>
this neceſſity becauſe we have ſtill guiltie conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, therein they are more than beaſts: for the guiltineſſe of our conſciences is not for this, that there needeth any ſacrifice to be offered to ſatisfie and purge ſinne: but through the remnants of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity which remaine in us becauſe of the weakenes and imperfection of our faith. for in theſe we are not to looke to any ſatisfaction yet behind, but to take hold of that perfect one which hath already ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied. If that act of theirs be propitiatory, then is not ſinne fully diſcharged by the other. Thus blaſphemous they are not onely in this their God of dough, but alſo in all other their ſatisfactions for ſinne, and in their doctrine of Purgatory. For if there remaine any ſatisfaction or purgation to be <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> are fully charged be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e God for <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>made, then is it not true that he hath made perfect for ever, neither was his death then of full and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient price. True it is, that although we are by his one oblation fully and perfectly diſcharged for ever before God, from the guiltineſſe of our ſinnes: yet we are not in the full poſſeſſion of this benefit, nor ſhall not be untill the laſt day, for then ſhall his enemies be made his footeſtoole. The Divell, ſinne and death are theſe enimies which he hath overcome, that they cannot raigne over us: but yet we muſt in the meane time wreſtle with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not therefore eſteeming the power of Chriſts death to be the leſſe, becauſe they be not already utterly aboliſhed, as the wicked unbeleeving Papiſts do, and therefore ſet up traſh of their owne to deſtroy ſinne, but waiting for that appointed time, when the full power of his death ſhall appeare: in the
<pb facs="tcp:21094:15"/>
meane time ſtaying by faith, and reſting our ſelves on that one ſacrifice once offred. To conclude then, hath not the mighty ſpirit of God power to apply unto us the vertue of that bloud: but ſuch ſilly virmin as the Popiſh prieſts muſt helpe? The holy ghoſt calling upon us, and teaching us to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply <note place="margin">Gods ſpiri<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies to us<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> death of C<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>theſe benefits, willeth us to draw neere with a true heart, with full aſſurance of faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 22. we come unto him with the heart, after a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall manner, becauſe all things in him are ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, we are bid to approch to lay hold of him by faith, for we can not either with the hand or with the mouth. And ſeeing there is not ſo much as one ſentence in all the booke of God, which ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of any application of his death any other way, it muſt needes be concluded againe that they may be as good prieſts as the prieſts of <hi>Baal</hi> and no<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and that when they hold up their idol, Chriſt is not betweene their fingers. Let us go forward. It ſhall yet be more manifeſt by the words of the holy Ghoſt, that this ſacrifice of the maſſe is ſo farre from being the ſacrifice of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that it doth flatly goe againſt it. For he ſaith as concerning Chriſt, that he did not offer himſelfe often, as the high prieſt went yerely into the holy place with other bloud, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. <hi>ver.</hi> 25. and then in the next verſe he giveth a reaſon, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that <hi>then hee ſhould have ſuffered often ſince the beginning of the world.</hi> This ſentence is very mighty againſt the Papiſts, becauſe it driveth them from all their ſhifts, and leaveth them naked and deſtitute: but the force of it will not appeare un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:21094:16"/>
we looke upon what principles it is grounded, to prove that if Chriſt ſhould have offred himſelfe often, then muſt he alſo have ſuffered death often ſince the beginning of the world. Among the which this offereth it ſelfe as the firſt to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that all the holy fathers, the Patriarches and Prophets, from the beginning could have no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance unto God but by remiſſion of ſinnes, and that whereas otherwiſe they had the dore ſhut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, by this they were reſtored into favour and received. For it cannot be denyed, but that by nature they were ſinners as we be: and that God cannot receive ſinners. Being therefore out of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie that they obteined life, it muſt needes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that they had pardon: for if either there had beene no ſinne, or no pardon to be graunted, what neceſſity could there be of a ſacrifice? The ſecond principle without which the reaſon of the Apoſtle cannot ſtand is this, that <hi>there can bee no remiſsion but onely by the ſacrifice of Chriſt:</hi> for if any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſacrifice, or any other way or meane might ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it, then were there not a neceſſity, why hee ſhould often ſuffer. For although there were a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of remiſſion of ſinnes, unleſſe all ſhould be damned, yet he might be ſet free from the ſame ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of offring himſelfe, ſeeing there were other wayes to obtaine it, but the holy Ghoſt ſtandeth upon this as a matter not to be doubted of, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there is, nor never hath beene any thing able to deſtroy ſinne, or to take away the guiltineſſe of it by makeing ſatisfaction, but onely the ſacrifice of the Sonne of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21094:16"/>
For howſoever the idolatrous Infidels do aſcribe unto many things the power of purging, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying for ſinne: yet the holy word of God, and thoſe which beleeve it do give that glory onely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, and euen as his great glory, wherein he hath no fellow. The third thing without which, an exception might be iuſtly taken againſt the foreſaid reaſon is this, that there could be no oblation of Chriſt, but he muſt ſuffer death: for when he ſayeth he ſhould not offer him ſelfe often, he addeth this cauſe, that then he ſhould have ſuffred often. It were and eaſie matter, if the offring of Chriſt were any thing available without ſuffring death, to ſay there were no neceſſity wherefore he ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer often, ſeing he might be offred, and not be ſlaine. But this is ſtrengthened by that which goeth before in the ſame <hi>Chapter,</hi> where he hath ſhewed that <note place="margin">Heb. 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>
               <hi>the teſtament is confirmed when men are dead, becauſe it is of no force while the Teſtator liveth,</hi> and ſo he is the Mediator of the New Teſtament, but yet through death. Wherefore alſo the former teſtament, in which there were but the ſhadowes and paterne of heavenly things, was ratified by death, as it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by this, that it was not dedicated without bloud. For when <hi>Moſes</hi> had read the law unto the people <hi>he tooke the bloud of Calues and Goates, with water, and purple Woll and Hyſſop, he ſprinkled both the booke and the people, ſaying, this is the bloud of the Testament which God hath commanded unto you,</hi> Likewiſe alſo <hi>he ſprinkled the Tabernacle and all the ministring veſſels with bloud, and almost all things, ſayeth he, by the law are purged with bloud, and without ſhedding of bloud,
<pb facs="tcp:21094:17"/>
there is no remiſsion.</hi> Here is then a manifeſt reaſon wherefore Chriſt could not be offred often, but he muſt then alſo dy often: even becauſe the teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is of no force without the death of the teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</p>
            <p>Here is further ſhewed wherefore it cannot be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailable without death, that is to ſay, <hi>there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of ſinnes without ſhedding of bloud.</hi> Chriſt therefore could not be offred often, unleſſe it ſhould be to no purpoſe, which is moſt abſurd, but his bloud muſt be often ſhed. Then if the Papiſts wil uphold and maintaine that their ſacrifice is availe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to purge away ſinne, and that it is a ſacrifice propitiatory for the quicke and the dead, as they do impudenly affirme: Let them alſo confeſſe that they murther againe the Sonne of God, and ſo ſhead his bloud. For if they will ſtand to this, that theirs is an unbloudy ſacrifice, and though they offer him, yet they do not ſlay him, and yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all do challenge the power thereby to purge ſinne: let them know that they goe directly againſt the ſpirit of God which ſaith, <hi>there is no remiſsion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſhedding of bloud.</hi> In this therefore they are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an horrible manner blaſphemous, that they will overthrow the reaſon and argument of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt. For if by any manes there might be a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to take away ſinne without the ſhedding of bloud, then might Chriſt have beene often offered and have dyed but once. If the fathers had the fruit and benefit of that one oblation, as namely their ſinnes waſhed away with that bloud once ſhed, and that without any offring of ſuch unbloudy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21094:17"/>
to apply the ſame: why ſhould not wee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by faith obtaine the ſame, unleſſe ſome ſhave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling offer him dayly? Ye blinde Idolaters, did the bloud of Chriſt purge away ſinne before his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, onely through faith, and ſhall it not now? Was there a more perfect power in it to aboliſh ſinne, in the fathers which were longe time before his comming, than there is after it hath beene ſhed indeede? For if it be ſo that the fathers had their ſinnes waſhed away with Chriſtes bloud, and yet no offring of him to apply the ſame, but apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded through faith, ſhall it not deſtroy the vertue thereof, or at the leaſt diminiſh it, when they teach that wee cannot be partakers of him, unleſſe he bee ſtill offered? Is that which the holy Ghoſt ſpeaketh, <hi>that he hath been once made manifeſt in the end of the world, to aboliſh ſinne, by the offring himſelfe</hi> to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred onely to the fathers before his comming? Doth not the reaſon following extend it unto us as well, yea even unto the whole Church, untill his comming againe at the worlds ende? for he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth it in this manner: that <hi>as it is appointed unto men to dye once, and after commeth judgement: ſo Christ alſo being once offred to take away the ſinnes of many, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe that looke for him ſhall appeare the ſecond time without ſinne, unto ſalvation.</hi> It is the ordinance of God that when a man hath runne his race and fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed his courſe, he ſhall not be permitted to turne backe againe to doe that which he left undone, or to make ſtraight that which is crooked, but muſt hold him unto judgement for things paſt, becauſe that onely remaineth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21094:18"/>
In like ſort he ſetteth the perfection of the one ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Chriſt, who being once offered to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſinnes of many, it is ſo perfectly done, that when he ſhall appeare againe the ſecond time to give the eternall ſalvation, there ſhalbe no ſinne to be purged, or for which he is to make further ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For when it is ſaid, that <hi>he ſhall appeare with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne the ſecond time,</hi> it is not meant of his own perſon, but of thoſe whom he hath redeemed from their ſinnes: which is moſt cleare and manifeſt in this, that the minde of the holy Ghoſt, is to ſhew a difference betweene his firſt and ſecond appearance, even in that point. Which if it ſhould be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of his owne perſon ſhould make no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, becauſe he was without ſinne at his firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, although he tooke upon him, and bare in his body the ſinnes of his people: But at his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond appearance becauſe he hath utterly deſtroyed ſinne for ever, there ſhal be none to be borne of him, and therefore none for which he ſhall againe offer ſacrifice.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts, but that they be impudent, might be aſhamed to patch in their trumpery, to give pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er unto the death of Chriſt, when they ſee here the perfection of it ſo ſet forth, that it hath ſo at once for ever deſtroyed ſinne, that there needeth no more ſacrifice to be offred. For will they make the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of it leſſe ſince his comming than it was before? We may then conclude, ſeeing the ſacrifice of the New Teſtament, that ſhould have a ſpirituall, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly, and endleſſe power could not be offred in a worldly ſanctuary, with worldly ordinances: the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21094:18"/>
ſanctuary and all the ordinances of the Popiſh ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and prieſtſtood are ſuch, as are earthly, and <note place="margin">All the Popi<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ſervice is ear<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note>ſeeing the ſame ſacrifice could not be offred to be available, unleſſe it were offred by the eternall god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, the Popiſh Prieſts are men and not God: and being the bloud of a man which is alſo God, that purgeth away ſinne, it hath an eternall power to purge: and ſo unleſſe the Papiſts will have a new redemption, there is no place for their propitiato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſacrifice. And ſeeing the ſacrifice that is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect is but once offred: that which is often offred doth not take away ſinne. And becauſe the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of <hi>Chriſt</hi> once offred hath for ever <hi>perfectly abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed ſinne,</hi> the promiſe of the <hi>New Testament</hi> is <hi>that God will no more remember it:</hi> and therefore no more ſacrifice to be required.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts contrary to that promiſe make ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions ſtill and ſacrifices for ſinne. Their ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice is offred often. Chriſt could be offred but once, becauſe he could dye but once. The ſacrifice is not available without death <hi>becauſe there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion</hi> 
               <note place="margin">No ſacrifice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailable with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bloud</note>
               <hi>of ſinnes without ſhedding of bloud.</hi> The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts do not ſay they ſlay Chriſt, they ſay theirs is an unblody ſacrifice: there is no remiſſion of ſins without ſhedding of bloud. The ſacrifice of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie is not the ſacrifice of the New Teſtament, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it be propitiatory, as they bragge, for the quick and the dead.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Note this, oh you Papiſts.</note> Nay it is as abominable before God, as if a man ſhould offer a dogge in ſacrifice. Then conſidering what injury theſe Prieſts after the order of Rome, have done unto the Sonne of God, firſt in chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21094:19"/>
that office and dignity, which belongeth onely unto him: and ſecondly, in overthrowing the perfection of the vertue and efficacy of his ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. Let as many of us, as minde to cleave unto Chriſt, to take part with him, and to fight under his banner, and ſo attaine the reward of eternall glory, remove ourſelves utterly from the campe and ſociety of ſuch adverſaries: and armed with the ſpirituall armour of God, let us ſound the trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and bid defiance againſt them, and againſt the divell, and Antichriſt their chiefe captaines; for this is moſt certaine, that we ſhall never be reputed <note place="margin">Note this.</note>as friends unto Chriſt, unleſſe we be at enmity with his enemies, and fight againſt them.</p>
            <p>Many do ſuppoſe that they may hold friendſhip and familiarity with them, and eſteeme of them as Chriſtians, and match their ſons with their daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, although they beare the ſame print, and be of the ſame ſtampe with their parents: onely becauſe they doe profeſſe the name of Chriſt, and carry a zeale unto him. But this doth bewray a moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible blindneſſe, and groſſe darkeneſſe in them, which cannot ſee, that to confeſſe the name of Chriſt is not any thing at all available, ſeeing they doe under that pretence rob and ſpoyle him of his glory, and tread downe his trueth, an deſtroy his lawes. The Apoſtle ſayeth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>that the Iewes had the zeale of God,</hi> but yet he ſayeth, <hi>it was not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to knowledge,</hi> and therefore that being not ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, but a carnall zeale, could nothing at all cleere them, but that they were ſtill thoſe which as utter enemies of God did fight againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21094:19"/>
In like ſort although it be graunted that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts have a devotion towards Chriſt, yet what doth it helpe them, ſeeing it is a carnal and blind de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion? <note place="margin">Note.</note>our Saviour Chriſt ſheweth <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. <hi>that the Scribes and Phariſes did build the tombes of the Prephets and garniſh the ſepulchres of the righteous<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſaid, that if they had beene in the dayes of their fathers they would not have beene partakers with them in the bloud of the Prophets:</hi> but yet for all this their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe and good will to honour the Prophets and to diſalowe of their fathers in killing them hee threateneth them, that all the righteous bloud ſhed upon the earth, ſhould come upon them, and why? becauſe he would ſe nd <hi>Prophets, and wiſe men and Scribes unto them: and of them they ſhould kill and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie: and of them they ſhould ſcourge in their ſynagogs, and perſecute from citie to citie.</hi> They were then gull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <note place="margin">Note.</note>and had their part in the bloud of the former Pr<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>phets, becauſe they murthered thoſe of their time. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s wicked and bloudy generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Papiſts: they have ſuch a zeale to the Saints of God that were of old, that they would honour them with divine worſhip, when as in the <note place="margin">Marke this y<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> generation of Papiſts.</note>meane time they perſecure and murther all thoſe which unbrace and follow the doctrine of thoſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ones. Shall not they then be guilty of all the bloud of the Martyres whom they ſeeme to love and honour, as the Scribes and Phariſes did the Prophets, when as by all kinde of cruell trecheries, by treaſons and perjuries, they ſeeke to murther, and deſtroy all thoſe which beare any love to the glorious Goſpell of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and that
<pb facs="tcp:21094:20"/>
will not fall downe and worſhip the beaſt nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his marke?</p>
            <p>If ever there were helhoundes that could not be ſatisfied with bloud, theſe are they which would ſpare neither high nor low, Prince nor ſubject, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ſts the <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>teſt Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> that ever <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eupon earth <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the moſt <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>udy.</note>yong nor olde. If ever there were damnable he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes, and abominable idolaters upon earth, theſe are they, which ground all their worſhip up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the diviſes of men, rejecting the holy ſcriptures, and taking the honour due unto God and his Son Chriſt, and giving it unto creatures, worſhipping for God <hi>a cake</hi> made of flower. Is it not then full time that we give eare to the voice from heauen: <hi>Come out of her my people, that ye be not partakers of her ſinnes, and that ye receive not of her plagues? Revel</hi> 18. 4. Is it not plainely ſaid by the Angell, <hi>Revel.</hi> 14. 9. <hi>that if any man worſhip the beaſt, and his image<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſhall receive the marke in his forehead, or in his hand, he ſhall alſo drinke of the wine of the wrath of God, even of the undelayed wine, which is powred forth into the cup: of his wrath, and he ſhalbe tormented with fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, in the preſence of the holy Angels, and in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lambe, and the ſmoke of their torment ſhall aſcend world without end: and they ſhall have no rest day nor night which worſhip the beast and his image, and if any receive the print of his name.</hi> Being as cleere as the Sunne at noone dayes, unto all thoſe which have eyes to ſee, that Rome is that Babylon, and the Pope that ſavage and cruell beaſt, ought it not to drive us as far from them as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, to renounce their religion, and falſe idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous, worſhip, to pack up all their traſh, and ſend it
<pb facs="tcp:21094:20"/>
home to Rome, to aboliſh their lawes, to flye their fellowſhip and ſociety, to be at utter enmity with them in this reſpect that they be the ſworne enemies of Chriſt? What honour is there left unto the Son of God, when ſuch vile caitifes ſhall take uppon them to be partakers with him in the office and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the mediatorſhip? For when as the ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and enmity betweene God and men was ſuch, that there could be no agreement nor unity, becauſe God is moſt perfctly holy and pure, and can not but hate that which is foule, and contrary unto his nature: there was none to approch unto him to be the mediator betweene him and them, which was in ſo high favour as that they might be accepted through him, nor of ſuch power as to be able to aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, and diſcharge whatſoever they could be char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged withall: but ſuch an one as was alſo moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and pure. While the Tabernacle did ſtande and the moſt holy place which did repreſent heaven, the high Prieſt was the mediator: for when the people were ſhut forth, he went in before the Arke to offer and make prayer for them. But thoſe things were but ſhadowes, and his conſecration was carnall. He was a poore ſinfull man, not able to purchaſe favour for himſelfe. He was a Prieſt agreeable to that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, but no wretched ſinner can be the mediator of the new covenant, to ſtande betweene God and the people, that he may obtaine favour and remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinnes for them, but he which is unſpotted. Alas what caſe then are thoſe men in, which take a poore Popiſh Prieſt, which is an uncleane ſwine in lechery, to be their Prieſt to ſtand betweene God
<pb facs="tcp:21094:21"/>
and them, to offer for them, that by him they may have their ſinnes pardoned? Doth not <hi>David</hi> ſay, the wicked cannot ſtand before God? How then ſhall any of them ſtand as a Prieſt before him to be a mediator? Doth not the holy Ghoſt ſay by <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> that the ſacrifice of the wicked is an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Lord? can that which the Lord doth eſteeme as a thing abominable, be a ſacrifice propiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atory? Can that which God doeth curſe and hate, clenſe away ſinne? The Lord in mercy open the eyes of poore ſimple men which have been ſeduced and miſled, that they may ſee what a deceipt this is, that a man ſhal be made to ſeeke life in that which is one of the greateſt ſinnes that can be committed, as namely, to ſet a poore rotten worme in the place and office of Chriſt, a vile filthy ſinner is to come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God with a ſacrifice. Now as they be idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous peieſts, by their cake which they worſhip as God, overthrowing as much as lyeth in their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the ſacrifice of Chriſt, and fighting under the banner of the diuell againſt God, ſo alſo their fruits do follow accordingly, and declare what manner of trees they be. Do they not maintaine lying and perjury, all kinde of diſembling, and falſe trecheries to obtaine their purpoſes, and to bring their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous and diveliſh practiſes to effect? Are they not bloudy murtherers and traitors againſt their lawfull Soveraigne Prince? Let them ſhew where ever <hi>Peter, Paul,</hi> or any Apoſtle of Chriſt hath taught the like, or put it in practiſe. If not then, let us conclude againſt them, that they be of their father the divel, who is the author of all falſhood, and a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21094:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
murtherer, the worker of all treaſons againſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And let all men which have any care to ſave their ſoules be ſo farre from liking of them, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to them, that they can ſay with the holy Prophet, <hi>do not I hate them that hate thee, O Lord, am I not irkeſomely greeved with thoſe that riſe up againſt thee? I hate them with a perfect hatred, I take them as enemies to my ſelfe.</hi> This zeale ought to be for the glory of Chriſt in all true Chriſtians, this loue ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the hearts of al faithful ſubjects towards their Prince. There is no teſtimony of any goodnes in men without this: for thoſe men which can retaine ſo willingly even in their boſoms theſe vipers, as ſome doe their wives, their ſonnes, their daughters; their ſervants, and their friends: although they make ſome ſhew, as though they did ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what miſlike, yet they be very Atheiſts, voide of all true knowledge, and feare of God.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
